Walt Kuhn Family Papers and Armory Show
Archives of American Art, Smithsonian Institution
- Armory Show Records, 1912-1963, Series 1:; (Boxes 1-2, 27-31, OV 36; 3.6 linear feet)
  - Retrospective Materials, 1939-1963, 1.9:
    This series consists of materials related to retrospective accounts of the Armory Show from the 25th and 50th anniversaries of the exhibition, in 1938 and 1963. Items from the 25th anniversary include an article by Frank Crowninshield in Vogue magazine, and Walt Kuhn's pamphlet, "The Story of the Armory Show" (1938), which was later reprinted in the Art News annual of 1939. Additional items in this series, including a typescript catalog, a series of photographs of the Armory building exterior dated 1962, and reproductions of clippings and artwork, seem to have been gathered for the 50th anniversary exhibition held in 1963. The reproductions in this series were not made from the Armory Show records in this collection. Additional documents related to the Kuhn pamphlet can be found in the Walt Kuhn Family Papers (Series 4).
    - Proof of Frank Crowninshield Article for Vogue1940, (Oversized material housed in Box 27) (Box 2, Folder 41)
    - Clippings, 1939, 1940, 1950, 1962-1963, (4 folders, including copy; oversized material housed in Box 27) (Box 2, Folder 42-45)
    - Exhibition Catalog, circa 1963 (Box 2, Folder 46)
    - Pamphlet, "The Story of the Armory Show," 1938 (Box 2, Folder 47)
    - Photographs, 1962 (Box 2, Folder 48)
    - Reproductions, circa 1963, (2 folders, including copies; oversized material housed in Box 27) (Box 2, Folder 49-50)
    - Oversized Proof of Frank Crowninshield Article for Vogue, (Oversized material scanned with Box 2, F41) (Box 27)
    - Oversized Clippings, (Oversized material from Box 2, F42) (Box 27)
    - Oversized Reproductions, (Oversized material from Box 2, F49) (Box 27)
- Association of American Painters and Sculptors (AAPS) Records, 1911-1914, undated, Series 2:; (Box 3; 0.2 linear feet)
  This series documents activities of the AAPS aside from the production of the Armory Show. Items include the group's constitution, documents related to incorporation, a minute book documenting their first meetings, multiple drafts of minutes of subsequent meetings, and briefs and correspondence relating to John Quinn's work to lift duties on imported art. Correspondence includes responses from exhibition venues around the country to queries made by Walt Kuhn in 1912 regarding the possibility of exhibiting members' artwork, along with a list of recipients in Kuhn's handwriting; letters accepting or declining invitations to membership; written resignations; and letters establishing proxies for the annual meeting of May 18, 1914. Lists of members are filed with membership correspondence. Records of the 1914 meeting, the first general membership meeting after the Armory Show and the last such meeting the group would hold, include tallies of votes to elect new officers and handwritten letters of resignation.
  Additional insight into the origins and politics of the AAPS can be found in Series 4.2: Walt Kuhn Letters to Family (1911, 1913, and 1914). All materials related to the planning, production and business of the Armory Show are filed in Series 1.
  This series has been scanned in entirety.
  - Constitution and Incorporation, 1911-1912 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Correspondence (Box 3)
    - Exhibition Venues, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Membership, 1911-1912, undated (Box 3, Folder 3)
      lists
      [illegible]
      Aiken, Charles Avery
      Anderson, Karl
      Bellows, George
      Borglum, Gutzon (see also Prendergast, Charles E. and Constitution and Incorporation)
      Borglum, Solon
      Calder, A. Stirling
      Fry, Sherry Edmundson
      Gregg, James Frederick
      Hassam, Childe
      Hillis, Newell Dwight
      Kramer, Edward Adam
      Porter, Bruce
      Prendergast, Charles E.
      Prendergast, Maurice B.
      Quinn, John (see also Constitution and Incorporation and Quinn brief)
      Spingarn, J.E.
      Tucker, Allen
      Wier, J. Alden
    - Miscellaneous Correspondence, 1912 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Minutes, 1911-1914, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 5-6)
  - Minutes (copies), 1911-1914 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Quinn Brief Against Duty on Works of Art, 1912-1913 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Records of the Meeting of May 18, 1914 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Records of the Meeting of May 18 (copies), 1914 (Box 3, Folder 9-10)
- Kit Kat Club and Penguin Club Records, 1909-1923, 1926, undated, Series 3:; (Box 3, 32, OV 37-38; 0.5 linear feet)
  Items in this series relate to the two artists' clubs in which Kuhn was heavily involved in New York. The annual costume balls of both clubs are documented in this series, as well as exhibitions and other events put on by the Penguin Club.
  Artists's balls are documented in photographs, scripts, and printed materials. Photographs depict party-goers and performers in costume, including Kuhn, John Quinn, Frederick James Gregg, William Bahr, John Oakman, Charles Ferrand, Rudy Dirks, Jack Johnston, Gus Mager, and Wood Gaylor, among others who are unidentified. Several photographs were taken by New York photographer Jesse Tarbox Beals. Scripts or scenarios written by Walt Kuhn and Frederic Paul Lopère are also filed here. Kit Kat Ball Printed Materials include invitations, posters, and glossy, heavily-illustrated programs.
  Most of the Penguin Club material in this series was removed from a scrapbook during previous processing and is now arranged chronologically as a group. In addition to artists' balls, items from the scrapbook document exhibitions, a musical performance, and social events such as stag dinners, strawberry festivals, and summer outings. Types of materials include invitations, tickets, flyers, announcements, posters, exhibition catalogs, programs, and Penguin Club stationary. Two posters for Penguin Balls are by the cartoonist Alfred J. Frueh.
  Other Penguin Club materials include marked exhibition catalogs from 1917, with Kuhn's estimated and actual sales prices, a large poster designed by Kuhn for the 1917 Penguin Ball, and a 1923 flyer for a dinner honoring Horace Brodsky. An undated historical essay entitled "The Penguin" by George Spelvin, which may have been added to the collection at a later date, is accompanied by two photographs showing posters made by the Penguin Club for the Red Cross in 1918.
  Additional materials related to the Penguin Club and Kit Kat Club can be found in the Walt Kuhn Family Papers (Series 4).
  - Photographs from Artists' Balls, circa 1908, 1918, 1919, undated (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Artists' Ball Scripts, undated (Box 3, Folder 12)
  - Kit Kat Ball Printed Material, 1909-1914 (Box 3, Folder 13)
  - Dismantled Penguin Club Scrapbook, 1917-1919, 1926, undated, (4 folders; oversized material housed in Box 32 and Box 37) (Box 3, Folder 14-17)
  - Marked Penguin Club Exhibition Catalogs, 1917, undated, (Oversized material housed in Box 37) (Box 3, Folder 18)
  - Penguin Club Clippings, 1919, undated, (Oversized material housed in Box 37) (Box 3, Folder 19)
  - Penguin Club Flyer from Horace Brodsky Dinner, 1923, (Oversized material housed in Box 32) (Box 3, Folder 20)
  - Penguin Ball Poster by Walt Kuhn, 1917, (Oversized material housed in Box 38) (Box 3, Folder 21)
  - Penguin Essay and Photographs, undated (Box 3, Folder 22)
  - Oversized Items from Dismantled Penguin Club Scrapbook, (Oversized maerials scanned with Box 3, F16) (Box 32)
  - Oversized Penguin Club Flyer from Horace Brodsky Dinner, (Oversized maerials scanned with Box 3, F20) (Box 32)
  - Oversized Items from Dismantled Penguin Club Scrapbook, (Oversized maerials scanned with Box 3, F14-F16) (Box OV 37)
    (Includes Posters by Alfred J. Frueh)
  - Oversized Marked Penguin Exhibition Catalogs, (Oversized maerials scanned with Box 3, F18) (Box OV 37)
  - Oversized Penguin Club Clippings, (Oversized maerials scanned with Box 3, F19) (Box OV 37)
  - Oversized Penguin Ball Poster by Walt Kuhn, (Oversized maerials scanned with Box 3, F21) (Box OV 38)
- Walt Kuhn Family Papers, 1859-1978, Series 4:; (Box 3-26, 32-35, OV 39-55; 25.8 linear feet)
  This series contains records of Walt Kuhn's artwork, career, travels, personal and professional associations, family members, and work in vaudeville, film, and interior design. The bulk of material relating to Kuhn's career as a painter can be found in Kuhn's Letters to Family, General Correspondence, Selected Gallery and Exhibition Files, Provenance Files, and to a lesser extent in Financial Records, Notes and Writings, and Printed Materials. Walt Kuhn's Letters to Family, written to his father, wife, and daughter span his entire career and contain candid, personal accounts of his activities and many illustrations. Also included in the papers are biographical narratives and documents; records related to Kuhn's theater, film, and design projects; and original cartoons, drawings, sketches, and photographs. Audio recordings made in 1965 and 1969 contain the recollections of Kuhn's daughter, Brenda Kuhn.
  Annotations in pen or orange crayon found throughout this series were probably made by Vera Kuhn and should not be confused with dates marked in pencil by Archives staff during initial microfilming in the 1960s. Penciled dates on correspondence were taken from the postmarks of envelopes, which were disposed of during microfilming.
  This series is arranged according the following 12 subseries:
  4.1: Biographical Material, 1882-1972
  4.2: Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1901-1949
  4.3: General Correspondence, 1890-1966
  4.4: Selected Gallery and Exhibition Files, 1920-1966
  4.5: Provenance Files, 1910-1964
  4.6: Other Projects, 1869-1897, 1910, 1922-1941
  4.7: Financial Records, 1920-1961, 1972
  4.8: Notes and Writings, 1901-1972
  4.9: Printed Materials, 1908-1987
  4.10: Artwork, 1906-1952
  4.11: Photographs and Scrapbooks, 1859-1978
  4.12: Audio Recordings, 1965, 1969
  - Biographical Material, 1882-1972, 4.1:; (Boxes 3, 32; 0.5 linear feet)
    This series contains biographical documentation of Walt Kuhn, his wife and daugher, his father and mother, his in-laws, and their ancestors. Found in this series is a handwritten chronology containing notes on the Armory Show. Other types of material include additional biographical narratives and chronologies prepared by Walt Kuhn, Vera Kuhn, and others; identification cards, passports, death certificates and other official documents; obituaries; correspondence and notes on genaeology; published biographies; printed materials relating to Kuhn and Spier family homes; and medical records and correspondence. Artifacts include a framed dollar marked "first dollar earned by Walt Kuhn" and a medallion from art school.
    Additional autobiographical writings can be found in Series 4.8: Notes and Writings. More obituaries of Walt Kuhn can be found in the 1949 clippings in Series 4.10: Printed Materials. Wills and documentation of family estates are in Series 4.7: Financial Records. Additional biographical information can be found in the audio recordings of Brenda Kuhn in Series 4.13: Audio Recordings.
    The bulk of this series has been scanned with the exception of medical records of Walt Kuhn, Vera Kuhn and Brenda Kuhn.
    - Narratives and Chronologies (Box 3)
      - Walt Kuhn, 1927-1962, undated (Box 3, Folder 23)
      - George Spier, 1925-1936 (Box 3, Folder 24)
    - Personal Documents (Box 3)
      - Walt Kuhn Family, 1909-1959, undated (Box 3, Folder 25)
      - Francis Kuhn, 1889, 1926-1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 26)
    - Passports, 1925-1932 (Box 3, Folder 27)
    - Walt Kuhn Obituaries, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 28)
    - Woodlawn Cemetery, 1949 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    - Genealogical Research, 1944-1945, undated (Box 3, Folder 30)
    - Biographical Publishers, 1930-1950, undated, (2 folders) (Box 3, Folder 31-32)
    - Printed Miscellany, 1882-1885, 1906-1913, 1926, 1939, 1949, 1972, undated (Box 3, Folder 33)
    - Medical Records (Box 3)
      - Walt Kuhn, 1939, 1948-1949, undated (Box 3, Folder 34)
      - Vera and Brenda Kuhn, 1925-1957, undated, (3 folders) (Box 3, Folder 35-37)
      - Life Extension Institute, 1923-1928, undated (Box 3, Folder 38)
    - Artifacts, 1892, undated, (Oversized material housed in Box 32) (Box 3, Folder 39)
    - Oversized Artifact, 1892, (Oversized material scanned with Box 3, F39) (Box 32)
  - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1901-1949, 4.2:; (Box 3-5, OV 39; 1.7 linear feet)
    Walt Kuhn traveled frequently throughout his life for weeks and months at a time, and while away he wrote lengthy letters almost daily, first to his parents from art school in France and Germany in 1901-1903, and from 1909 on to his wife and daughter. His candid and detailed letters to his family reveal otherwise hidden motives and feelings regarding events, career, art, politics, and personalities. Scattered letters to Walt from Vera and Brenda are interfiled chronologically in this subseries, and are especially revealing of Vera's involvement in her husband's career.
    Occasionally, Kuhn writes from New York when Vera is out of town. Significantly, these occasions include the winter of 1911-1912, when he writes that "a new society" of artists is forming in reaction to the conservatism of the National Academy of Design, referring to the Association of American Painters and Sculptors, which would go on to mount the Armory Show of 1913. (For Kuhn's letters to his wife dealing directly with the Armory Show, dating from September 1912 to April 1913, see Series 1.1, Armory Show Correspondence, Organizer's Letters.) Other significant New York events described include Kit Kat Balls and Penguin Club events from 1914, 1917, and 1918.
    Kuhn advised several important collectors of contemporary art, sometimes traveling with them to make purchases, and his letters home include descriptions of the collections and studios they visit. Collectors include Marie Harriman (especially 1931, see also Selected Gallery and Exhibition Files), John Quinn (1913, 1918, 1919, 1920), and Florida collectors Bert and Olive Taylor, Josephine and Ernest Kanzler, and Paul and Mary "Minna" Mellon (1945, 1947). Conversations with Mary and A. Conger Goodyear and Lillie P. Bliss about the formation of the Museum of Modern Art are related to Vera in letters from 1928 and 1929.
    Kuhn's letters home reveal attitudes towards artists and other colleagues, as well as his many personal and professional prejudices. A painting trip to Paris in 1933 brings news of publisher Alfred Skira, and the artists Pablo Picasso, Demetrius Galanis, Man Ray, Cecil Howard, and Andre Derain. Letters from Ogonquit, ME, report on other artists who worked nearby, such as Edwin Booth "Ted" Grossman, Bernard Karfiol, John Laurent, John Carroll, Patsy Santo, and Yasuo Kuniyoshi. From 1940 to 1942, a house on Lake Buel in Great Barrington, MA serves has a studio where Kuhn paints and tutors Mary Harriman Rumsey, Lily Emmet Cushing, and Harry Whitney, among others.
    As designer and writer of vaudeville productions in the 1920s, Kuhn wrote home from the road about the politics and personalities of backstage life. Casts of his shows included performers Raymond Hitchcock and Lee Morse. During business trips for the Union Pacific railroad from 1936 to 1948, Kuhn wrote letters home about regional art and society circles throughout the Midwest and West. Significant Western contacts include artists Ralph Stackpole, Otis Oldfield, Rinaldo Cuneo, Edward Weston, critic Arthur Millier, collector Walter Arensburg, and film celebrities Cecil B. de Mille and Gary Cooper.
    Kuhn's habit of writing to Vera when separated from her continued during his final illness and hospitalization in 1948 and 1949. Letters from this period are marked by his deteriorated mental state.
    Illustrations are often found in Kuhn's letters, especially those written during painting trips to Paris, Maine, Colorado, Massachusetts, and Florida. Additional illustrated letters are filed with Artwork and with Photographs and Scrapbooks.
    Photographs and photographic postcards are found throughout the series. Among them are photographs of the Gottlieb Reber estate in Lausanne, Switzerland in 1931; Arizona in 1928; and Florida in the 1940s. Many of the photographs mentioned in letters are filed in Series 4.11: Photographs and Scrapbooks.
    Significant enclosures include letters from Charles Sheeler in 1922 and 1924, an exhibition catalog and floorplan for a Montross Gallery exhibition of 1914, and an original print of a nude by Kuhn, sent in 1918. Other enclosures were separated and may be filed elsewhere in the Kuhn Family Papers.
    Correspondence is arranged chronologically. When undated, the sequence of letters has been determined from their contents, with undated letters placed at the end of the month or year, if known, or at the end of the series. Other personal and business correspondence is filed in General Correspondence and throughout the collection. See individual series descriptions for more detail.
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1901 (Box 3, Folder 40)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1902 (Box 3, Folder 41)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1903 (Box 3, Folder 42)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1906, 1909 (Box 3, Folder 43)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1911 August-September (Box 3, Folder 44)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1911 October-November (Box 3, Folder 45)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1911 December (Box 3, Folder 46)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1913 July (Box 3, Folder 47)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1913 August-September (Box 3, Folder 48)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1914 January-March, undated (Box 3, Folder 49)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1915-1917 (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1918 (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1919 (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family (copies), 1919 (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1920, undated (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1922, undated (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1923 February (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1923 June-December (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family (copies), 1923 (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1924 (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1925, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1927-1928 (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1929, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 13-14)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1931, (2 folders (Box 4, Folder 15-16)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1932, 1933 (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1934-1935 (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1936, undated, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 19-20)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1937 (Box 4, Folder 21)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1938, (2 folders) (Box 4, Folder 22-23)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1939 (Box 4, Folder 24)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1940 May-July (Box 4, Folder 25)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1940 August (Box 4, Folder 26)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1940 September-October (Box 4, Folder 27)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1941, (4 folders) (Box 4, Folder 28-31)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1942, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 32-34)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1943 (Box 4, Folder 35)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1944, (3 folders) (Box 4, Folder 36-38)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1945, undated, (8 folders; oversized material housed in OV 39) (Box 5, Folder 1-8)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1946 (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1947, undated, (3 folders; oversized material housed in OV 39) (Box 5, Folder 10-12)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1948, undated, (2 folders) (Box 5, Folder 13-14)
    - Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, 1949, undated (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - Oversized Enclosures in Walt Kuhn Letters to Family, (Oversized material scanned with Box 5, F1 and F10) (Box OV 39)
  - General Correspondence, 1890-1966, 4.3:; (Box 5-9, 32, OV 40; 4 linear feet)
    Correspondence in this series is primarily between Walt Kuhn and his professional and personal contacts and spans his entire career. Correspondents include family members, fellow artists, students, dealers, museum and gallery staff, collectors, friends, fans, critics and colleagues. Copies of outgoing correspondence are often present and are interfiled chronologically. Also included is scattered correspondence of Vera and Brenda Kuhn, and correspondence written after Kuhn died that documents his family's efforts to exhibit, sell, and donate his work.
    The content of the correspondence ranges from personal and candid to purely transactional. Artists, collectors, dealers, and critics involved in the creation of significant works of art and collections in the early 20th century are represented. An alphabetical index of selected correspondents in this series is provided in the appendix. Another resource for accessing correspondence are the card files in Series 4.8: Notes and Writings, where correspondence with various contacts was indexed by the Kuhns and filed alphabetically by name.
    In 1938, Walt and Vera Kuhn wrote and self-published the pamphlet, "The Story of the Armory Show" and sent it gratis to hundreds of interested parties. Among the correspondence from that year are many heartfelt reponses from fellow artists and other witnesses to the 1913 event, including Charles Sheeler, William Glackens, Stuart Davis, André Derain, Henri Roché, Walter Pach, and J.H. du Bois to name just a few.
    Kuhn regularly instructed students through the mail with lengthy letters about painting techniques and methods. San Francisco painter Otis Oldfield is represented by over 100 lengthy letters in this subseries. Kuhn's letters to Oldfield, returned at Kuhn's request in 1945 for a publication project that was never realized, are interfiled. Other correspondence students include Patsy Santo, Frank di Gioia, Watson Bidwell, John Bernhardt, John Laurent, Goldie Paley, and Eric Lundgren. See the appendix for dates.
    Types of material include letters (sometimes illustrated), postcards, invitations, announcements, and Christmas cards, which are sometimes made of original artwork. Enclosures are often found, such as photographs, clippings, tracings of art work, writings, receipts, passes and membership cards. Some letters indicate enclosures that were previously separated and can be found in other series.
    Significant writings enclosed with correspondence include an early vaudeville script written by Kuhn and his friend, Archibald Macnab (1923); drafts of articles about Kuhn by the poet Genevieve Taggard (1931), critic Alan Burroughs (1930), and patron Eloise Spaeth (1950); and an unpublished history of the 1913 Armory Show by Paul Bird (1938). Photographs and photographic postcards are also found throughout the series. Included are photo postcards from Spain and France (1925), and from Arizona and California (1928); and photographs related to Kuhn's work for the Union Pacific Railroad Company (1936, 1938).
    Additional correspondence can be found throughout the collection. See individual series descriptions for details.
    A list of selected correspondents from this series can be found in the Index with cross-references to correspondents found in 4.4: Selected Gallery and Exhibition Files, and 4.5: Provenance Files.
    Index to Selected Correspondents in Series 4